Hirsch, Felix and Elisabeth; Papers ger042
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Felix and Elisabeth Hirsch Papers
1902-1980
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger042
3.24 cubic ft.
The collection contains biographical and professional materials of Felix Hirsch, librarian and professor of history, as well as a small amount of matrials of his wife Elizabeth F. Hirsch, a specialist in Renaissance philosophy.
Biographical History
Born in 1902, Felix Hirsch was a native of Berlin, Germany. He received a Ph.D. in history from Heidelberg University in 1923. Hirsch was editor of various German newspapers before he came to the United States in 1935. He earned a degree in library science from Columbia University and became a librarian at Bard College at Annandale-on-Hudson, NY in 1936. He also served as a professor of history at Bard until 1954. In 1955, he became librarian and professor of history at Trenton State College in New Jersey, retiring in 1972.
He died in December 1982 at the age of 80, survived by his wife, the former Elisabeth Fesit, two sons and four grandchildren.
Elisabeth (Fesit) Hirsch was born in 1904 in Mainz, Germany, but grew up in Berlin. She received her Ph.D. in Philosophy and History from the University of Marburg, immigrated to the United States in 1938, and married Felix that same year. After raising their two sons, she began teaching at Bard College and, beginning in 1956, was Professor of Philosophy and Modern Languages at Trenton State College.
She died in May 1998 and was survived by two sons, four grandchildren and one great-grandchild.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains biographical materials, correspondence, manuscripts of books and articles, as well as academic lectures of Felix Hirsch. The collection also includes some correspondence and offprints of Elizabeth F. Hirsch, a specialist in Renaissance philosophy.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated by Elisabeth Hirsch and transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives by John Spalek in June 1984.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of two files noted.
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence; Publications, serial.; Hirsch, Elisabeth Feist, 1904-1998; Hirsch, Felix, 1902-1982
- Aachner Kunstblätter, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- AAUP (American Association of University Professors) Bulletin, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Academic Papers and Lecture Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bei Albert Schweitzer in Günsbach, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The American-German Review, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Historical Review, 1963; 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- American Library Association, 1944; 1951; 1959; 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Die Amerikanische College-Bibliothek, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Anthropos - Internationale Zeitschrift für Volker und Sprachenkunde, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Archiv für Reformationsgeschichte, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Articles about Felix Hirsch, 1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Articles by Elisabeth Hirsch, 1957 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
- Articles by Felix Hirsch, 1929-1930; 1932; 1934-1935 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
- Articles by Felix Hirsch, 1936; 1942-1943; 1945-1948 (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
- Articles by Felix Hirsch, 1951-1954 (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
- Articles by Felix Hirsch, 1953-1955; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Articles by Felix Hirsch, 1955-1958 (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
- Articles by Felix Hirsch, 1959-1960; 1965-1966; 1968-1969 (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
- Articles by Felix Hirsch, 1971; 1973-1975; Undated (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
- The Association of College and Research Libraries, 1940; 1942; 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Autour de Michel Servet et de Sebastien Castellion, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bard Alumni Magazine, 1961; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bard College House Lease, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bard College Middle States Evaluation, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- The Bard College News Letter, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Bibliotheca Docet, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bibliothèque D' Humanisme et Renaissance (Humanisme et Renaissance), 1957; 1961; 1970-1971; 1973; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Bibliothèque D' Humanisme et Renaissance (Humanisme et Renaissance), 1980; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Bismarcks Glaube - Neuer Beitrag zum Thema: Staatsmännisches Genie und Religion, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Books Abroad: An International Literary Quarterly, 1937; 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Canadian Institute of International Affairs, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Centro De Estudos Filógicos, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Christian Advocate, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Church History, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Clippings of General Interest Articles, 1928; 1933 (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
- Clippings of General Interest Articles, 1934-1935 (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
- Clippings of General Interest Articles, 1943; 1951-1952; 1954; 1956; 1970 (Oversize 1, Folder 10)
- Columbia University Quarterly, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- The Commonweal, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- The Contemporary Review, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Crisis and Decline of West Berlin, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- The Crisis of East Germany, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- The Crisis of German Liberalism, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Current History - A Monthly Magazine of World Affairs, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Current History - A Monthly Magazine of World Affairs, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Current History - A Monthly Magazine of World Affairs, 1950-1952; 1954 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Current History - A Monthly Magazine of World Affairs, 1960; 1963; 1966; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- The Decline of Empires, Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Deutsche Literaturzeitung, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Dreußischte Jahrbücher, 1929; 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Drexel Library Quarterly, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- The Economic Journal, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Edizioni Scientifiche Italiane, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- "Eduard Von Simson - Das Problem der Deutsch-Jüdischen Symbiose im Schatten Goetthes und Bismark", Undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Elisabeth Feist Hirsch Correspondence, 1966-1968; 1970-1971; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Elisabeth Feist Hirsch "Heideggers' Message to the Present Generation", Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Elisabeth Feist Hirsch "Is President Vargas a Dictator?", Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Elisabeth Feist Hirsch Thesis - "Erfahrugen bei der Durchnahme der 'Minna von Barnhekm,' des 'Nathan der Weisse' und des 'Tasso'", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Elisabeth Feist Hirsch "Portugal and the War-Time Allies", Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
- "Europa-Union Deutschland" Presentation Poster, 1965 (Flat-file 1, Folder 1)
- Encyclopedia of Library and Information Science, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Felix Hirsch Academic Records - RESTRICTED, 1920; 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Must consult an archivist in order to view this material.
- Felix Hirsch Academic Records - RESTRICTED, 1923; 1935 (Oversize 1, Folder 11)
- Felix Hirsch Birth Certificate, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Felix Hirsch Correspondence, 1932-1936; 1939-1941; 1943; 1954-1956; 1961 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Felix Hirsch Correspondence, 1963-1966; 1973; 1975-1976; 1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Felix Hirsch Resignation from Bard College, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- "Frankfurt, 1848 and 1948: The Problems of German Liberty and Unity", Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Ffh Mitteilungen Herausgegeben von der Fofschungsstelle für den Handel, Berlin, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Forum, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Friedrich Ebert, Gedanken zum 50. Todestag, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Friends Intelligencer, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Friends Journal, 1961; 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "George P. Gooch - Young at Ninety - The Last of England's Great Historians from Victorian Days", Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Die Gegenwart, 1954 (Oversize 1, Folder 12)
- Gegenwart im Rückblick, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Geschichte in Wissenchaft und Unterricht, 1965; 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Die Große Überlicht - Kulturpolitiche Zweimonatschafte, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Gustav Stresemann Manuscript, Undated (Oversize 1, Folder 13)
- Gustav Stresemann Manuscript, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Heidelberger Jahrbucher, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Heinz Krekeler, 1973; 1975-1976; Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Historische Vierteljahrschrift - Zeitschrift für Geschichtswissenschaft und für Lateinische Philologie des Mittelaters, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Heliand, Verlag, Luneburg, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Henry Everling zum Gedächtnis", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Die Hilfe - Zeitschrift für Politik, Wirtschaft und Geistige Bewegung, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Interlibrary Loans from the College Viewpoint, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Isador Lubin Obituary, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- International Journal - Canadian Institute of International Affairs, 1954; 1957; 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Journal of the History of Philosophy, 1968; 1971; 1973; 1977-1978; 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Journal of the History of Philosophy, 1983; 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Journal of Modern History, 1946; 1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Joachim Tiburtius, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Junior College Journal, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Klett, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- "Krise und Niedergang des Deutschen Liberalismus", Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- "Der Künder der Huminität: Wilhelm von Humboldt und das Deutsche Judentum", Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Library Schedule, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Library Journal, 1943; 1954; 1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- The Library Quarterly, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- "Library Report, New Jersey State Teachers College at Trenton, 1954-1955", Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- "LJ: Letters", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- The Living Age - The World in Review, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Leo Baeck Institute, Year Book XX, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Louis S. Weiss, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- "Der Mann, der Brücken Schlug", Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Max M. Warburg, Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Merchants and Scholars, Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Memorial Service for Gerhard E.O. Meyer, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Der Morgen - Monatsschrift der Deutschen Juden, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- "Michael Melamid", Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- "Nationale Geistigkeit in ihrer Möglichen Betimmbarkeit", Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Der Naturschutz, Undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Die Neueren Sprachen, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- The New Leader, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- New Jersey Library Association Newsletter, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- New Jersey State Teachers College Library Staff Bulletin, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Notes on Conversation with Colleague, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Notícias de Portugal, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Otto Braun, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- "Overdruck Uit 'Het Boek'", Undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Photographs of Felix Hirsch, Undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Die Politische Meinung, 1960; 1969; 1976 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Politische Studien, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- The Portuguese Economy, Undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, 1951; 1953 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Publications de la Société des Études Rabelaisennes, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Public Opinion Quarterly, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Renaissance Quarterly, 1973; 1975; Undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
- The Renaissance Society of America, Undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
- The Review of Politics, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Review of "Portugal's Defense", Undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
- "The Revolution of the Intellectuals - Reflections on the Centenary of 1848", Undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Rheinische Lebensbilder, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Ruperto Carola, 1959; 1964-1966; 1968-1969; Undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
- The Saturday Review of Literature, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- School and Society, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Schweizer Beiträge zur Allgemeinen Geschichte, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "Sigmund Feist - Deutscher Germanist Jude", Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- The Sixteenth Century Journal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- The Social Studies for Teachers and Administrators, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- The South Atlantic Quarterly, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Why Special Collections in College Libraries?", Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Standards for Libraries", Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Stechert-Hafner Book News, 1953-1954; 1960; 1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "Stresemann; ein Lebdensbild Musterschmidt Verlag, Göttingen", Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- The Survey - Family Training for Parent and Child, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Survey Graphic, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Theologische Zeitschrift, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- "Together - 7th International Student Conference, Bard College", 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Translation of Elisabeth Feist's Birth Certificate, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- "Treitschke und das Judentum Seiner Zeit", Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Trenton State College Library Dedication, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Trenton State College Report of the Librarian, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Trenton State College's State Signal Student Paper, 1954; 1965 (Oversize 1, Folder 14)
- University of Coimbra, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- The University of Hawaii Press, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- "The University of the State of New York, The State Education Department - A Plan for Meeting College Library Problems", 1954 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- "The Use of the Book Collection in the Teaching Program of a Progressive College", Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Vierteljahrschefte für Zeitgeßchichte, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- "Weltbild und Staatsidee bei Jean Bodin", 1930 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Wilson Library Bulletin, 1936; 1944 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Zeitschrift für Geschichte und Altertumskunde Ermlands, 1956; 1958; 1960 (Box 3, Folder 27)